Ronald A. Kleemann
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Ronald A. Kleemann papers
circa 1942-2008
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Ronald A. Kleemann
2.0 linear feet
The papers of photorealist painter Ronald A. Kleemann papers date from circa 1942-2008 and measure 2.0 linear feet. The papers include chronological files that contain a wide variety of documents, projects files relating to his race car paintings, biographical materials, writings and lectures, printed material, original drawings, and photographs.
Provenance
Donated by Ronald Kleemann, November 11, 2009.
Related Material
The Archives of American Art also holds an oral history interview with Ronald A. Kleemann, 2009 Oct. 11-12, conducted by Judith Richards.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
The Photorealist painter Ronald A. Kleemann (b. 1937), who is well known for his renderings of automobiles, currently works and resides in Valatie, New York. Born in Bay City, Michigan, he moved to New York City to pursue art after graduating from the University of Michigan College of Architecture and Design in 1961. Kleemann is represented by the Louis K. Meisel Gallery, New York, NY.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of photorealist painter Ronald A. Kleemann papers date from circa 1942-2008 and measure 2.0 linear feet. The papers include chronological files that contain a wide variety of documents, projects files relating to his race car paintings, biographical materials, writings and lectures, printed material, original drawings, and photographs.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 7 series:
Series 1: Biographical Materials, 1971-2008 (Box 1; 0.1 linear ft.)
Series 2: Chronological Files, 1950s-2008 (Boxes 1-2; 0.8 linear ft.)
Series 3: Writings and Lectures, 2006 (Box 2; 0.1 linear ft.)
Series 4: Project Files, 1985- 2007 (Box 2; 0.4 linear ft.)
Series 5: Printed Material, 1971-2004 (Box 2; 0.2 linear ft.)
Series 6: Artwork, circa 1942, 1960s and 1970s (Box 2; 0.3 linear ft.)
Series 7: Photographs, 1980s-2002 (Box 2; 0.1 linear ft.)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects-Topical:
Painters--New York (State); Photo-realism
Types of Materials:
Drawings; Photographs
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Materials,1971-2008, Series 1:; (Box 1; 0.1 linear ft.)
  This series include resumes, press and racing pit passes, and an embroidered CART (Conceptual Art Racing Team) badge.
  Materials are arranged chronologically within each folder.
  - Resumes,1971-2005 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous,1972-2002 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Entrance Documentation to Car Races and the Super Bowl,1971-2008 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Chronological Files,1950s-2008, Series 2:; (Boxes 1-2; 0.8 linear ft.)
  Each annual file includes a variety of documentation such as drawings, sketches, school report cards, handwritten letters, correspondence, flyers, photographs, press releases, periodical clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs. The content varies from year to year.
  Of particular interest are photos of the artist at exhibitions, 1968 and 1971; a description of Kleemann's art van (Conceptual Art Racing Team "CART") at the 1977 Indianapolis 500; draft of a profile about the artist, 1979-1980; dissertation on photorealism, 1988; interview questions and dissertation on photorealism, 2000-2001; clipping and minutes from a project meeting to raise funds for COARC (Columbia County Association for Retarded Children) and art donations for auction, 2001-2002.
  Original order has been maintained. The years 1960, 1965 and 1995 are lacking.
  - Chronological Files,1950s (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Chronological Files,1961, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
  - Chronological Files,1962-1964, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 7-9)
  - Chronological Files,1966-1976, (11 folders) (Box 1, Folder 10-20)
  - Chronological Files,1977, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 21-22)
  - Chronological Files,1978-1994, (17 folders) (Box 1, Folder 23-39)
  - Chronological Files,1996-1999, (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 40-43)
  - Chronological Files,2000-2006, (7 folders) (Box 2, Folder 1-7)
  - Chronological Files,2007-2008 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Writings and Lectures,2006, Series 3:; (Box 2; 0.1 linear ft.)
  Among the lectures and addresses is the text of Kleemann's 2006 presentation to the Hudson Fortnightly Club.
  - Writings,undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Lectures and Addresses,2006, (Box 2; 0.1 linear ft.) (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Random Artist's Notes,undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Project Files,1985-2007, Series 4:; (Box 2; 0.4 linear ft.)
  Project files relate mostly to paintings of cars.
  This series is arranged alphabetically by project title.
  - Corvette Painting Studies,1985 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Jack Gordon Car Studies,2002 or later (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Kodak Car Studies,2002 or later (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - M and M Car Studies,2002 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Navy Painting Studies,undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Target Car Studies,undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Tony the Tiger Car Studies,2002 or later (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Viagra Painting Studies,2002 or later (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Zurich Painting Studies,2007, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 20-21)
- Printed Material,1971-2004, Series 5:; (Box 2; 0.2 linear ft.)
  Printed materials include exhibition catalogs, NASCAR programs, and clippings.
  This series is organized by record type and material within each folder is filed chronologically.
  - Group Exhibition Catalogs,1971-1973 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - NASCAR Official Program Guides,1977-1979 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Periodical Clippings,1972-1992, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 24-25)
  - Advertisements,1971-2004 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Artwork,circa 1942, 1960s and 1970s, Series 6:; (Box 2; 0.3 linear ft.)
  All artwork is by Kleemann. The earliest drawings were made around the age of five.
  Original order has been maintained.
  - Earliest Drawings,circa 1942 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Random Studies,1960s and 1970s (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Abstract Studies,1960s and 1970s, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 29-30)
  - Miscellaneous Drawings,1960s and 1970s (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Photographs,circa 1980s-2002, Series 7:; (Box 2; 0.1 linear ft.)
  These photographs most likely served as source materials for paintings.
  - Photographs,circa 1980s-2002 (Box 2, Folder 32)